Finding Aid for Carl Rominger family papers, 1840-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carl Rominger family papers 1840-1945
Rominger family.
5 linear feet
85782 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, family. Family correspondence of Carl, physician and geologist, his wife Frederika, his son Louis, and his daughter Julia; journals, 1861-1905, of Carl Rominger, including notes on his expeditions as State Geologist of Michigan, and other travels through New York, Missouri, Arkansas, Kentucky, and Ohio; and miscellaneous scrapbooks and account books; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was transferred from the University of Michigan Graduate Library (donor no. 1278 ) where the papers had been donated by Rominger’s daughter Marie Rominger in 1937. A smaller portion of the collection came from Dr. and Mrs. Robert H. Haskell (donor no. 3772 ) in 1961.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
A microfilm copy of portions of the correspondence series (1845-1855) is available.
Carl Ludwig Rominger was born December 31, 1820 in Schnaitheim, Württemberg. He studied at the University of Tübingen, 1839-1844, graduating with a medical degree. He then became an assistant at the university's chemical laboratory. At this same time, he received a gift of money to prepare geological studies of portions of Germany, France, Austria, Switzerland among other countries.
He emigrated to the United States in 1848 where he both practiced medicine and continued his geology and paleontology studies. He moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1859. In 1872, Rominger was appointed state geologist of Michigan, serving until 1885.
He died April 22, 1907
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical and genealogical material; Correspondence; Miscellaneous and other papers; Notebooks from courses at Tübingen, 1839-1842; Carl L. Rominger notebooks and journals, 1861-1905; and Drafts and manuscripts of various writings.
The notebooks and journal are especially rich documenting Rominger's interest in geology, paleontology, and allied fields in New York, Missouri, Arkansas, Kentucky, Ohio, with the bulk pertaining to Michigan where Rominger served as state geologist.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Geology--Michigan.; German Americans--Michigan.; Michigan. Geological survey.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Fifth Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Furnishings.; Interiors.; Neuman family.; Rominger, Carl Ludwig, 1820-1907.; Rominger family.; Rominger House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Rominger, Carl Ludwig, 1820-1907.; Rominger, Frederika, 1826-1914.; Rominger, Julia.; Rominger, Louis, 1859-1936.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical and genealogical material
  - Genealogical material (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1840-1945
  (largely written in German)
  - [fragmentary] (Box 1)
  - Undated, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1840-1844 (Box 1)
  - 1845 (Box 1)
    (microfilm copy available)
  - 1846 (Box 1)
  - 1847-1849 (Box 1)
  - 1850 (Box 1)
  - 1851 (Box 1)
  - 1852 (Box 1)
  - 1853 (Box 1)
  - 1854, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1855 (Box 1)
  - 1856 (Box 1)
  - 1857 (Box 1)
  - 1858-1859 (Box 1)
  - 1860-1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1880 (Box 1)
  - 1881-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906-1913 (Box 1)
  - April 1914, letters of condolences upon the death of Mrs. Carl Rominger, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - May 1914-1920 (Box 1)
  - April 1921, letters of condolence upon the death of Julie Rominger, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - April 1921 (Box 1)
  - May 1921 (Box 1)
  - June 1921-1945 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Carl Rominger and James Hall, photocopies (Box 1)
    (originals at the New York State Library)
- Miscellaneous and other papers
  - Scrapbook, scattered dates, containing obituaries of Rominger family members (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1846-1922 largely clippings, letters of condolence, 1907 and ephemera (Box 2)
  - Account books 1860-1870 of Dr. Carl Rominger, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Expense book circa 1877-1890 including accounts of the Geological Survey of Michigan; and miscellaneous later accounts (Box 2)
  - Account book circa 1891-1904 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea concerning Schnaitheim (Ger.) and the Carl Rominger Silver Medal (Box 3)
  - Historical sketch of flour mills in Ann Arbor and vicinity (Box 3)
  - Autograph book of Marie Rominger (Box 3)
  - Album of Wilhelmine Mayer containing poetry, drawings, and ephemera (Box 3)
  - Book of Silhouettes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Rominger family portraits (Box 3)
    - Carl Rominger House, including interior furnishings, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Neuman family, Ann Arbor (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Notebooks from courses at Tübingen 1839-1842
  - Pflanzenphysiologie von Hugo Mohl 1839-1840 (Box 3)
  - Allgemeine Botanik von Hugo Mohl 1840 (Box 3)
  - Allgemeine Chirurgie von Rieke 1840 (Box 3)
  - Physiologie des Menschen von Rapp 1840 (Box 3)
  - Allgemeine Pathologie von Gmelin 1840-1841 (Box 3)
  - Materia medica von Gmelin 1841 (Box 3)
  - Pathologische Anatomie von Rapp 1841 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous and untitled notebooks 1840-1842 (Box 3)
- Carl L. Rominger notebooks and journals 1861-1905
  (includes title used by CLR with occasional misspellings)
  - [Vol. 1] 1861 "Suspension bridge and Lockport" (Box 4)
    contains also "Expense for Geol. Survey June 1876"
  - [Vol 2.] 1863 (Box 4)
    (volume includes sections titled:
    "Excursion to Widder, Canada W"
    "Excurs, to Alpena ..."
    "Excurs. to Sandusky"
    "Capture of the Boat by Southern rebels" (there are no notes on the capture of the boat)
  - [Vol. 3] 1868-1877 (Box 4)
    (Notes on trips beginning October 8, 1868, May 18, 1869, May 9, 1870, May 22, 1877)
  - [Vol. 4] 1871, "Diary from Mai 2, 1871" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 5] 1871, "C. Rominger... Escanaba.. ." (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 6] 1871-1874
    (includes segments titled:
    "Dubuque meeting of A.A.S."
    "Excurs. to Rockford, Iowa ..."
    "Expenses for Geol. Survey, Mai, 1871"
    "Expenses for Geological Survey, 1873"
    "Expenses 1874"
    "Fossilien nach Europa"
  - [Vol. 7] 1871, "Diary from August 1, 1871" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 8] 1871, "Diary October 4, 1871" (Box 4)
  - [Vo/ 9] 1872, "Diary Mai 2, 1872 C.R." (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 10] 1872, "C. Rominger Dezb. 1872 memoranda" (Box 4)
  - [Vol 11] 1873, " Mai 1873" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 12] 1873. " Juli 1873.. .Saginawbay.. .Lake Erie.. " (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 13] 1873. "Cleveland Black Shales... Waverly group" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 14] 1874 "Geol. Diary May 1874 C. Rominger" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 15] 1874, "Diary August 1874" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 16] 1875 "Diary May 18, 1875 C. Rominger Exploration of Rifleriver.. Alabaster.. .Monroe... Lake Superior.. ." (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 17] 1877 "Diary for the Explorations of the Geolog. Survey of Mich. during the year 1877 by C. Rominger" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 18] 1877 (August 21 and on) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 19] 1877 (September) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 20] 1878 (May 15 and on) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 21] 1878 (August 21 and on) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 22] 1879 (May 8 and on) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 23] 1879 (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 24] 1880, (May 27 and on and August and on) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 25] 1881 (May 14 and on) (Box 4)
  - [vol. 26] 1882 (May 23 and on) (Box 4)
    contains also notes beginning September 15, 1880)
  - [Vol. 27] 1883 (May and July) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 28] 1884 (May 20 and on) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 29] 1887, "Excursion to Mount Stephen and Vancouver Island" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 30] 1888-1889 Notes from September 14, 1888, March 25, 1889 (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 31] 1889, Notes from August 12, 1889 (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 32] 1890, Notes from March, 1890 (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 33] 1893, (August 21 and on) "C. Rominger, Ann Arbor, Mich. 1893" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 34] 1895 (June 24 and on) "C. Rominger, Ann Arbor, Mich. 1895" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 35] 1896 "C. Rominger, Ann Arbor, Mich." (Box 4)
    (also contains notes dated July 7, 1896 and on, June 1, 1898 only, and June 13, 1900 and on)
  - [Vol. 36] 1897, "Excursion to Tennessee phosphate districts... August examinations of the environs of La Salle.. ." (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 36] "Catalogue of Star corals prepared March 1874" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 39] "Register of Fossils Collected during the progress of the Geological Survey of Michigan" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 40] Miscellaneous notes (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 41] "The Medical News Visiting List" -- contains "Mikroscopic sections of Monticuliporoids", etc. (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 42] "Corallen u. Bryozoen.. .", etc. (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 43] "Ausstände im Jahr 1878" (personal accounts) (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 43] Geological data (Box 4)
    (two pages only)
  - [Vol. 45] "Memoranda for the Montreal Excursion" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 46] "Fossilien... Hamilton group im Thunderbay" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 47] "Fossilien... Le Anse" (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 48] Black thin case with notebook containing a few pages in German. (Box 4)
  - [Vol. 49] "Register of fossils Collected 1904, 1905 Environs of Louisville, Ky." (Box 4)
    (There are newspaper clippings within front cover; contains also lists of fossils dated June 25, 1898, Dezbr. 9, 1898, Febr. 1, 1905 July 25, 1905)
  - [Vol. 50] Various (Box 4)
    (Includes segments titled:
    "Register of Fossils found in Certain Localities"
    "Register of Corals in my Collection on January 1, 1906"
    "Register of Pamphlets... U.S. Government''
  - [vol. 50] Diary (no year given) beginning: "left Louisville... 19 June at noon. .; contains also "Enumeration of fossils collected in Autumn 1904 at Louisville Ky.'' (Box 4)
- Drafts and manuscripts of various writings
  - Geological Survey of Michigan, articles, and unidentified (Box 5)
Related Material
Rominger's survey maps (ca. 100 maps) have been separated from the collection and cataloged.